<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Life of an engineer</title>
    <link>http://example.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Life of an engineer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 12:13:55 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://example.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Only Skill That Matters</title>
      <link>http://example.org/posts/book_review_1/book_review_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 12:13:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/posts/book_review_1/book_review_1/</guid>
      <description>This book is worth reading, here are a few points that stuck with me:
We, as humans, are on the verge of exponential growth, which if we look back for tech, is true. Meaning, there is an enormous amount of opportunities out there. Maslow’s hierarchy of needs is how humans work. I have first learned about the hierarchy back in college, in an elective class. I was mind-blown, and was thinking “it all makes sense!</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This book is worth reading, here are a few points that stuck with me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We, as humans, are on the verge of exponential growth, which if we look back for tech, is true. Meaning, there is an enormous amount of opportunities out there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maslow’s hierarchy of needs is how humans work. I have first learned about the hierarchy back in college, in an elective class. I was mind-blown, and was thinking “it all makes sense!”.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, you need food, water, oxygen, and rest; simply take care of your physical needs. Then you need to feel safe, are you safe during your daily life? Then you need to build intimacy with friends and relationships and feel like you belong somewhere. It often makes me think as if you belong to a tribe :) Then you need to feel accomplished, and develop your self-esteem. Among my peers, this is often the step I see people struggle with. Then after that, you can realize yourself, and achieve your full potential&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maslow%27s_hierarchy_of_needss&#34;&gt;Maslow&amp;rsquo;s Hierarchy of Needs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have a print-out of this at the office. Reminds me that I am a human being.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you know how to learn?
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are adapted to learn things that are vivid, visual, and experiential. That will trigger any kind of your senses in your brain. We are certainly not that good at learning from books, or textbooks, or boring lectures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So kind of “learning by doing” as I am learning by writing here :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The author puts this as “to learn like a caveman”. As caveman smells and wonders and explores and learns!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience is a great way to learn, something experimental, something that you can materialize with your hands and acknowledge with experience, is a great way to learn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The main requirements for learning:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foundation: base on what you already know, compare or contrast with the things you know. All of the human knowledge is somehow connected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need to know: “Why?” Ask this to yourself, always. Ask “why do I need to learn this? When am I ever going to use this?”. The word &amp;ldquo;use&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;need&amp;rdquo;, meaning how it is practical to you, is very critical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Readiness: Have a pressing and immediate need to learn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orientation: Start with a problem and work toward a solution. Step by step. Have a way or setup that will allow you to play with solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-Concept: Get involved and make your own path during learning. This is why many online courses actually allow you to take different paths while learning, different readings and topics for you to learn. “Reclaim some ownership over your experience”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motivation: The drive to learn must come from within you. No one ever can force you to learn. This is why I got a couple of Cs and Ds in my bachelor&amp;rsquo;s, as I never saw the need to learn these courses. I still don’t :).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you prepared to learn? The plan is the key to success, and planning for your learning, laying out steps to follow are critical for learning.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deconstruct the whole topic into smaller pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the core 20% of the topics, and learn them first, as it would probably give you the most understanding of the topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sequence the small pieces and put them into order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put high stakes, pressure yourself, and psychology to condense your timeline and push yourself to learn faster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In general, two things, put these into your mind, “pressing need” and “immediate use”!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The author puts this in a nicer cleaner steps:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why am I learning this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What level of understanding or knowledge do you need?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can this information be broken down into small parts? How can it then be recombined into broader categories or themes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the most important things to learn based on my personal goals?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the right order?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will I actually access this information?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How’s your study schedule? How can you compress timelines?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will I measure and track my progress?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What will I do if things don’t go to plan?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So that’s about learning, what about your memory? Memory is probably the most critical part of your mind, the better it functions, I can tell you will be more successful and realize yourself better.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You cannot know something unless it is securely stored in your memory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The answer lays in visual memory. Remember those memorization contests? Those contestants use visual storage rooms, with practice, they can memorize more than usual humans can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create weird visualizations of items that you want to remember. The stranger the better. Create these “markers”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another technique is “memory palace”. Google the phrase, it is an amazing technique to learn a big chunk of data and store them in memory. Simply put, it is creating weird imagination of the things that you want to remember and pick a room that you know the best in your head, and place the data at the corners of that room. It works, needs practice, but it works. I highly recommend you read about this further.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you sustain and not lose your learning? Humans lose memory exponentially. The key to avoiding this is “repeated, spaced repetition”. I integrated this practice into my daily life and I am already seeing it is working.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look into Anki, Memrise, and Brainscape. All are based on this idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also recommend Readwise. It reminds you of excerpts from the books you have read, daily basis, and uses SRS (Spaced Repetition System). &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaced_repetition&#34;&gt;SRS @Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prime your mind to learn: Quickly survey the thing you will learn, prepare your mind for learning, prime it, and make it more curious about why you are learning this. This is called “pre-reading”, and it is so important that you do this, before learning anything. From what you pre-read, ask some questions to yourself, such as “what viewpoint do I expect from the author?”, “who might agree or disagree?”. Ask some questions, to put your mind on high alert and motivated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another thing: speed reading. It requires a lot of practice but when you get there it is impressive. I have a friend that can speed read and it is crazy. I just need to practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brute force learning: Learn it from multiple resources. Not every resource is the same and you cannot just try to learn from one place. If one does not work for you, do not force yourself, find some other resource to learn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloom’s Taxonomy. I have a print of this hanging in my office. Here is the picture below. This is the key to become the best in any field. I will leave you to look at the picture, it is very self-explanatory. Print this, make this your phone wallpaper. It is that important.
&lt;img src=&#34;http://example.org/Blooms-Taxonomy.png&#34; alt=&#34;Scenario 1: Across columns&#34;&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try teaching the topic you want to learn. Richard Feynman’s way. &lt;a href=&#34;https://fs.blog/feynman-learning-technique/&#34;&gt;Feynman learning technique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eat well, no sugar and low carbs, exercise, and most importantly, have a high sleep quality. Remember the first step of Maslow’s hierarchy of needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
